{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "BritishphilosopherG.E.Moorewroteafamous\"defenseof\"thisphrasethatinspired his later \"Proof of an External World.\" This phrase titles a pamphletthatarguesitisabsurd for an island to rule a continent and which advocates for replacing the Magna Carta with a Continental Charter. For ten points, give this two word phrase that titles a Thomas Paine pamphlet advocating for American independence, a term which indicates obviouslycorrect beliefs. ANSWER:Common Sense(accept \"A Defence ofCommonSense\") (2) A commission made up of, in part, Founding Father Gouverneur Morris drew the plans for this city between the modern streets of Houston and 115th. The Stonewall Inn Riots of the late 1960s occurred in this island's Greenwich Village. The DirectoroftheNew Netherlands Peter MinuitsupposedlyboughtthisU.S.islandfortwenty-twodollarsworthof beads and other trading goods. Fortenpoints,namethisisland,themostdenselypopulated New York City borough. ANSWER:Manhattan(orManhattanIsland; prompt on\"New York\", \"New York City\", or \"New York County\"; prompt on \"The City\") (3) This period began after Visigothic nobleman Pelayo [[peh-LY-oh]] rebelled against Governor Munuza, establishing the Kingdom of Asturias. Large parias tributes were paid during this period,whichbeganwiththeBattleofCovadonga.Thisperiodincludedavictory over the Almohads at Las Navas de Tolosa, and this period ended with the conquest of Granada by the Catholic monarchs ofCastileandAragon.Fortenpoints,namethisperiodin which the Iberian peninsula was \"reclaimed\" from Muslim kingdoms. ANSWER:Reconquista (4) A play in this genre depicts the general Cleon as a slave to Demos,whoseaffections are vied for by a sausage-seller named Agoracritus [[ah-gor-AH-krih-tus]]. Menander [[meh-NAN-der]] worked in the \"Athenian New\"schoolofthisgenre,whereasits\"Old\"form is seen in plays like The Knights and The CloudsbyAristophanes,whomadefunofSocrates. For ten points, name this lighthearted and often satirical ancient Greek genre of plays, contrasted with Tragedy. ANSWER:Comedy(accept Ancient GreekComedy; or AthenianComedy; accept Old, Middle, or NewComedy) 2021-22 C Set History (5) A month before his death, this man prepared a 42-page manuscript criticizing the Compromise of 1850, to be read by his ally, Senator JamesMurrayMason.Thismanandhis wife Floride [[\"FLORIDA\"]] perpetrated the Peggy Eaton affair during the Jackson administration. With Henry Clay and Daniel Webster, this politician formed the \"Great Triumvirate\" of influential elderstatesmen.Fortenpoints,namethisSouthCarolinasenator and seventh vice president of the United States.",
      "answer": "John CaldwellCalhoun"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1992, this modern nation invaded its eastern neighbor in an attempt to protect the independence of the region of Nagorno-Karabakh. TalaatPashaorderedforcedmarches through the SyrianDesertbythisnation'snamesakeethnicgroup,killingoveronemillionof them. Multiple wars with Azerbaijan have been fought by, for ten points, what Caucasian nation that faced a 20th century \"Genocide\" under the Ottoman Empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Republic ofArmeniaorHayastani Hanrapetut’yun",
        "acceptArmenian Soviet Socialist Republic",
        "orHaykakanSovetakan Soc'ialistakanHanrapetut'yun",
        "Armenian Genocide"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with acting as watchmen, freedmen known as vigiles [[VIH-jih-less]] worked in this profession, often using a substance called acetum [[AH-keh-tum]]. Men in this profession in Ancient Greece used ox intestines as a flexible hose. Thefirstbrigadeofthese people in Rome notoriously refused to do their job untildistressedcitizensnegotiatedwith Crassus over the saleoftheirhomesforminimalprices.Fortenpoints,namethisprofession held by people who put out blazes. ANSWER:Firefighters (acceptFiremen; orFirewomen) (8) This man was given the name \"Big Turtle\" after becoming the adopted son of Chief Blackfish following his capture by the Shawnee. This former Quaker led an expedition to scout the area which became the Wilderness Road. This head of the TransylvaniaCompany founded a namesake \"Borough,\" one of the first colonial settlements west of the Appalachians. The Cumberland Gap was blazed by, for tenpoints,whatpioneerwhosettled modern Kentucky?",
      "answer": "DanielBoone"
    },
    {
      "question": "This actress gave a four-day tour duringtheKoreanWarcalled\"AnythingGoes.\"The nation of Egypt unilaterally banned this actress's films due to her conversion to Judaism following her marriage to Arthur Miller. At Madison Square Garden, this actress performed \"Happy Birthday, Mr. President\" for then headofstateJohnF.Kennedy.ThefilmSomeLikeit Hotfeatures, for ten points, which cultural iconand actress from the mid-20th century?",
      "answer": [
        "MarilynMonroe",
        "Norma JeaneMortenson",
        "or Norma JeaneBaker 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Barbar Temple in modern Bahrain is dedicated to a god of this domain, the Sumerian deity Enki. Duringearly conversion efforts, Spanish colonists equated the biblical episode of the \"Binding of Isaac\" to instances of child-sacrifice to the Aztec god of this domain, Tlaloc. The citizens of Athens supposedly rejected the gift of a god of this domain, which took the form of a spring. For ten points, name this primary domain ruled by Poseidon. ANSWER:Water(accept theOcean; or theSea; acceptrain; prompt on \"rivers\" or \"storms\") BONUS: The Lady of the Lake emerged from the water to give this sword to Arthur. Its scabbard supposedly prevented blood-loss, leading Merlin to state it was the greater treasure. ANSWER:Excalibur(acceptCaledfwlch;Calesvol; orCaliburnus) (2) This disease's primary vector of transport was discovered by Paul-Louis Simond [[see-MOHND]] while in Bombay during its \"third\" major breakout. The most prominent symptom of this disease is the inflammationoflymphnodesinthegroin,neck,andarmpits. This disease iscausedbythebacteriumYersiniapestis,andhistoricallyspreadthroughblack rats carrying fleas aboard merchant vessels. For ten points, name this disease that killed about one third of the European population in a pandemic called the Black Death. ANSWER:BubonicPlague (prompt on \"Black Death\" or\"Black Plague\" before mentioned; prompt on \"plague\") BONUS: Simond discovered that fleas carry the plague after being transferred to Bombay from Paris in 1897 by a non-profit Institute bearing the name of what French chemist who developed the vaccine for rabies and anthrax, as well as a namesake method for treating milk?",
        "answer": [
          "LouisPasteurorPasteurInstitute",
          "acceptPasteurization 2021-22 C Set History 3 This location's Main Building is built in the French Renaissance style and was awarded a gold medal at the 1900 Paris Exposition. This location's namesake \"special\" allegedly forced people to change their names. Between 1892 and 1954, nearly twelve million people were processed at this facility. For ten points, name this island that was the busiest immigration inspection center intheUnitedStates,nowpartoftheStatueofLiberty National Monument. ANSWER:EllisIsland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another island in New York is this one that houses the city's notorious main jail complex. Due to low crime rates inNewYorkCity,thatfacilityonthisislandwasvotedtobe closed by 2026. ANSWER:RikersIsland (4) The Treaty of Fort Stanwix set Indian Territory's southern border at this river, settlement near which sparked Lord Dunmore's War. This river was known as the \"River Jordan\" by enslaved people, who often had to cross it to escape North. Fort Pitt was constructed where this river is formed from the Allegheny and Monongahela [[mah-non-gah-HEH-lah]] Rivers. For ten points, name this river that forms the southern border of Indiana and a namesake midwestern state. ANSWER:OhioRiver BONUS: The Great Lakes region, including the Ohio River Valley, was the site of fighting during what indigenous uprising against British rule following the French and Indian War, led by a namesake Odawa war chief? ANSWER:Pontiac's War (accept \"Conspiracy\" or \"Rebellion\"in place of \"War\"; accept Pontiac; orObwaandi'eyaag) (5) This regime's Admiral of the Fleet was assassinated by royalist Fernand de la Chapelle, who hoped to place Henry VI[[thesixth]]onthethrone.AsaresultofCaseAnton, this regime's naval secretary Gabriel Auphan [[oh-FAHN]] scuttled its fleet at Toulon [[too-LOHN]]. This state facilitated \"round-ups,\" like at Vel' d'Hiv [[VEL DEEV]], to deport Jews to Nazi camps. For ten points, name this collaborationist regime of France during World War Two, led by Philippe Petain [[peh-TAHN]]. ANSWER:VichyFrance (or Régime deVichy; acceptFrenchState; orÉtat français; prompt on \"France\" alone; do not accept \"Free French\" or \"Free France\") BONUS: The Free French who opposed the Vichy Regime were led by thistankcommander who became president of France from 1959 to 1969.",
        "answer": "Charles deGaulleor Charles André JosephMariede Gaulle 2021-22 C Set History"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Natural Disasters in the U.S.",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "2005 Category-5 Hurricane which broke the levees of New Orleans.",
          "answer": "HurricaneKatrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Volcano in the Cascades whose 1980 eruption caused deadly mudslides that reached the Columbia River.",
          "answer": "MountSaint HelensorLawetlat'la"
        },
        {
          "question": "2017 Hurricane which left denizens of Puerto Rico without power for years.",
          "answer": "HurricaneMaria"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Naval Affairs in Antiquity",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Naval battle which ended Xerxes's invasion of Greece in 480 BC.",
          "answer": "Battle ofSalamis]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom in modern Somalia that heavily traded with its northwestern neighbor, Egypt.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom ofPuntorPwenet",
            "Land ofPunt 2021-22 C Set History"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Colonialism in Africa",
      "prompt": "Concerning French imperialism, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Kingdom which became a French protectorate following the Treaty of Fes.",
          "answer": "Kingdom ofMorocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African nation whose FLN fought a civil war with the French in the 1950s and 1960s.",
          "answer": "People's Democratic Republic ofAlgeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horn of Africa nation and neighbor to Ethiopia once known as French Somaliland.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic ofDjibouti",
            "République deDjibouti",
            "or JumhūrīyahJībūtī"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former West African colony whose first president, Leopold Senghor, founded the literary movement Negritude.",
          "answer": "Republic ofSenegalor République duSénégal"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A tribe who lives primarily in this region called the Pirahã [[pee-RAH-hah]] speak a language that notably lacks words for specific numbers. The Yanomami are (20 pts)",
        "another widely-studied native group from this region. The Vale do Javari [[hah-VAH-ree]] is a massive reserve for indigenous peoples in the Brazilian (10 pts)",
        "portion of this region. Indigenous rights and territories are threatened in, for ten points, what largest rainforest in the world? ANSWER:AmazonRainforest (accept FlorestaAmazônica;accept SelvaAmazónica) (2) Under the flag of truce, this rebellion's leader, James McFarlane, wasshotbya rogue soldier, leading to a marchonPittsburgh.This(+)insurrectionwascausedbya tax meant to allow the federal government to pay off Revolutionary War debts. The greatest domestic crisis of the Washington administration (*) was, for tenpoints,what Pennsylvania rebellion caused by a tax on alcohol? ANSWER:WhiskeyRebellion (accept \"Revolt\" or \"Insurrection\"for \"Rebellion\") (3) Christopher Marlowe was a member of this figure's counter-cultural circle known as the \"School of Atheism.\" This Governor of Jersey was tried and imprisoned in the Tower of London for (+) hisinvolvementintheMainPlot,anattempttodepose James Stuart. The word \"Croatoan\" was etched in a tree near the lost colony of Roanoke, which (*) was founded by this man. For ten points, name this Elizabethannoble who is the namesake of the capital of North Carolina."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir WalterRaleigh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In thisempire,theChakitakllawasafootplowusedbyfarmersduetoalackof large pack animals. This state employed chasqui [[CHAH-skee]] couriers, who kept record of transactions using the quipu [[KEE-poo]] knotted-string (20 pts)",
        "system. This empire experienced a civil war between Huascar and Atahualpa [[ah-tah-HWAHL-pah]]priortoitsconquestbytheSpanish. (10 pts)",
        "Fortenpoints,namethis Andean empire that was conquered in 1533 by Francisco Pizarro. ANSWER:Incan Empire (or theIncas; acceptTawantinsuyu;orRealm of the Four Parts; orFour Parts Together) 2021-22 C Set History (5) This politician and his wife, Lou, nursed injured soldiers in Tianjin [[TYAHN-JIN]] during the Boxer Rebellion. Douglas MacArthur ignored this president's order to halt the tear-gassing and eviction of the Bonus Army (+) camp under the guisethattheveteransplannedtooverthrowthegovernment.Shantytowns during the early Great Depression were named for this president. The Wall Street Crash of 1929 (*) occurred during, for ten points, what Republican's single presidential term?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "HerbertHooveror Herbert ClarkHoover",
        "acceptHoovervilles"
      ]
    }
  ]
}